For me, the most important question today is
私にとって 今日の一番の問題は、
how do we sit together and lead a discussion?
一堂に会しながら、 どのように討論をするか、ということ。
Not just with one or two persons, but all of us on this planet.
一人や二人ではなく、 世界中から集まった全員が、
To start to raise the questions about what's important.
なにが大切かを問うのだから。
-For me, what's important. -Are you bending the truth...
-私にとって、なにが大切か。 -真実を歪曲していない？
about climate change?
気候変動に関して。
Why are African states less developed than Western states?
アフリカの国々はなぜ、 西洋より発達が遅れているのか？
I'd like to know...
知りたいのは…
What is the proper balance between Jewish values
民主主義において、ユダヤの価値観と
and other values in a democracy?
別な価値観との適度なバランスとは？
-I have a few questions. -Why do they dislike Americans?
-いくつか、質問があります。 -彼らはなぜ、アメリカ人が嫌いなのか?
How does an individual relate to the group in the 21st Century?
21世紀における、 個人と集団の関係とは？
This place has a lot of history.
ここは、歴史的な場所です。
In this place, they used to burn books
ここで焚書事件が起こり、
by those who say things that other people don't like to know.
人々が聞きたくないことを 記した本が燃やされました。
And that's why we've come here to August-Bebelplatz in Berlin,
だから私たちは今日、 ベルリンのベーベル広場に集まったのです。
where books were burned, thoughts were burned.
書物が燃やされ、思想が燃やされ、
Freedom of speech was burned here.
言論の自由が燃やされたこの場所に。
THE TABLE OF FREE VOICES, BEBELPLATZ, BERLIN
自由な声のテーブル べーベル広場、ベルリン
It's wonderful to see all the beautiful faces around this table.
このテーブルを囲む、たくさんのいい顔を 見られて嬉しく思います。
We have a long day ahead of us, so we'll go right into the programme.
長い一日となりますので さっそく始めましょう。
Today, we ask and we begin
今日は、100の問いを投げかけ、
to discover answers to 100 questions
その答えを探そうという試みです。
chosen from thousands, donated by people from all around the world.
世界中から届いた、何千ものなかから 選ばれた問いです。
We will ask them all over the course of the next nine hours...
これから九時間にわたり、 これらの問いについて考えます。
In eight sessions of around 45 minutes
8回にわたる、 各45分ずつのセッションで
covering eight themes of global importance.
グローバルな重要性をもった テーマを取りあげます。
-Chinese. -From here. Directly from here.
-中国人です。 -ここの出身です。まさに、この地。
Have you been to my country?
私の国にいらしたことありますか？
No, unfortunately, I have not.
いいえ、残念ながら。
Together, we come together as one to celebrate our diversity
本日の会合は、 私たちの多様性を祝うため、
and to gather a multiplicity of viewpoints.
そして、多様な見解を募るためです。
-Thank you for being here with us. -At the Table of Free Voices.
-ご参加、ありがとうございます。 -自由の声のテーブルへようこそ。
-Question one. -From Anonymous, USA.
-問い １。 -匿名より、米国。
"What is today's most important unreported story?"
「今、最も重要で 報道されていないニュースとは？」
You can start with your answer.
どうぞ、お答えください。
What ought to be reported today
今、報道されるべきことだが
and definitely does not
明らかに報道されていないことは、
is how much life costs.
命にどれだけコストがかかるか、 ということ。
The price of life on this planet.
この惑星における命にかかるコスト。
We are going from crisis to crisis
私たちは危機から危機へと移るなかで
and we only report a portion of the story.
ほんの一部しか報じていません。
When the guns of battle are silenced,
銃声が鳴り止んだとたんに、
we then forget about that country,
私たちはその国のことを、
about that region that has suffered conflict.
紛争がくり広げられた 地域のことを忘れ、
And we go to report a different story, and when we do so...
次の別な報道を始めてしまいます。
Well, I would begin with Darfur,
まずは、ダルフールでしょうか。
with the extermination of populations,
民族の抹殺が
just because they're of another religion or another race.
宗教や人種が異なっている という理由だけで行われました。
And the world is not interested in them,
しかし、世界は関心を示しません。
because they have no resources, no oil.
そこには資源もなく、 石油も出ないから。
For me, the most unreported story of today
私にとって現在、 報道されていないニュースとは、
is the truth behind global terrorism.
グローバル・テロリズムに潜む真実。
We have no idea, really no idea,
私たちは知らない、 本当に何も知らない、
what the truth behind it is.
どんな真実が潜んでいるのか。
Who is alive? Who is dead?
だれが生き、だれが死んだ？
Who is advancing it? Who is pioneering it?
だれが進め、だれが始めたのか？
Who is making use of it
だれがそれを利用して得しているのか。
in "his" or "their" favour.
どの彼、あるいは彼らのために？
The children who have been enslaved.
奴隷にされた子供たち。
Human trafficking.
人身売買。
The millions of people crossing borders illegally
何百万という、 よりよい生活を求めて
in search for a better life.
不法に国境を越える人々。
I think today's most important unreported story
今日、最も重要で 報道されていないストーリーは、
is the story of the young girl who died
死んでしまった女の子のこと。
ten minutes ago of malaria.
ほんの十分前に、 マラリアで死んだのです。
She died needlessly,
それは、不必要な死でした。
because the drugs that would be able to kill the malaria parasite exist,
実際には、マラリアの治療薬が あるからです。
and are cheap.
しかも安価です。
But she didn't get those drugs.
しかし、彼女は薬を得られなかった。
And she died,
そして、死にました。
and just now another child died,
そして、またもう一人、 子供が死にました。
and this story goes unreported.
こういう話は報道されません。
I don't think there is
思うんだけど、
today's one most important unreported story.
今、報道されない最も重要なストーリーは １つだけじゃない。
There are many unreported stories throughout the world.
報道されないたくさんのストーリーが 世界中にあると思うの。
The good things that are happening in the world.
世の中で起こっている、 様々な良いこと。
We don't hear about the good things. There are wonderful things happening.
ふだんあまり聞かないけど、 すばらしいことがいっぱい起こっているわ。
All we ever hear about is bad news.
でも、耳に入ってくるのは、 悪いニュースばかり。
The death, the destruction, wars,
死、破壊、戦争。
killing, murders, rapes.
殺戮、殺人、レイプ。
Problems. If you squeeze a newspaper,
問題だらけ。新聞を絞ってみたら、
it seems to bleed.
血が流れるかと思うくらいだ。
Thank you.
ありがとう。
Question twelve from Judy Twedt,
問い12、 ジュディ・トゥイードから。
24, Denver, USA.
24歳、 デンバー、米国。
"Should we have the right to choose where we live?"
「我々は、住む場所を 自分で決める権利を持つべきか？」
Now, that's an interesting question.
さあ、これはおもしろい質問だ。
I like it.
いいですね。
We are just born.
私たちはただ、生まれてきます。
We're just born somewhere on planet Earth,
地球という惑星のどこかで生まれ、
and if we don't want to stay there,
そこに住みたくなかったら、
we go somewhere else.
別なところへ行く。
But then, when we do, we're discriminated against.
でも、それをすると たちまち差別を受けます。
I arrived two days ago and on the 11th I have to leave again,
僕は2日前に着きましたが、 11日には出国しなければなりません。
because my visa only lasts for four days.
ビザが四日分しかないから。
As a Colombian,
コロンビア人として、
as a citizen of the world,
世界の住人として、
I have no right to enter this paradise,
僕はこの楽園に足を踏み入れる権利がない。
the paradise of the First World, except for four days.
第一世界の楽園。 許されたのは、たったの四日間。
I believe we should have the right to choose where we live.
当然、どこで暮らしたいか 自分で決める権利があるべきだわ。
We live in a world where capital can move,
今の世の中、資本の移動も、
where goods can move.
商品の移動も自由でしょ。
Why is there so much hysteria about people moving?
なのに、なぜ人の移動に対して ヒステリックになるの？
For example, one time I wanted to go to Dubai,
一度、ドバイへ行こうとしたとき、
but because I have
私が入国に
a 1951 Geneva Convention passport,
1951年のジュネーブ条約に基づいた パスポートを見せたら
I was not allowed.
許可されなかった。
And the reason they gave me for this
その理由として、
was that I didn't belong anywhere.
私がどこにも属さないから、と。
Everybody wants to live in a place that is free of war.
だれだって、戦争のない国で暮らしたいさ。
Everybody wants to live a harmonious existence.
だれだって調和のなかで生活したい。
But some people can buy that and others cannot.
だが、それを買える人と 買えない人がいる。
Some people can lay claim to that right,
その権利を請求できる人もいれば、
and others are just not in a position to do so.
そんな状況にない人もいる。
Yes, we all should have the right to live wherever we want,
そう、だれもが望む場所に 住む権利を持つべきだが、
but all of us should be able to afford to do so.
だれもが、 それを支払える状況にあるべきだ。
Sometimes you have to move to be able to support your family.
家族を助けるために 移動しなければならない場合もあります。
If you're crossing borders, and you're not recognized by a state,
国境を越えて、 そこが自分を認めてくれない国だったら、
Does that mean you're illegal by definitions of the state?
その人は違法者になるの？ その国の定義だからって。
I think as humans, we can't say another human is illegal.
でも人間に対して、 違法な存在呼ばわりするなんておかしいわ。
The people who are moving are doing so,
人々が移動するのは、
because they are desperate.
絶望しているからです。
They're taking enormous risks.
多大なリスクを冒すほどに。
Look at the people arriving in the Canary Islands.
カナリア諸島にたどり着く 人々をごらんなさい。
Every week in makeshift boats,
毎週、急ごしらえのボートに乗って
they're arriving on the beach by the hundreds.
何百という人々が岸に流れ着きます。
These people are absolutely desperate.
その人々は、 完全に絶望しているのです。
Otherwise, they would not have left.
でなければ、 自国を離れなかったでしょう。
That's not a choice. That's not choosing where I'm going to live.
でも、あれが、生きる場所を 選んでいるといえますか？
You're not going to choose to risk nine chances out of ten of drowning,
十中八九、溺死するリスクや
or being killed before you actually arrive.
殺されるリスクを負うのですよ、 到着する以前に。
That's not a choice!
望むわけありません！
You could also ask the question, shouldn't we have...
あるいは、こんな問いはどうだろう？
the right to remain where we are?
いる場所に留まる権利があるべきか？
This is a very urgent question for many, many people on this Earth.
これは、地球上の多くの人にとって 切実な問いだ。
Tibetan people, such as myself, being Tibetan,
チベットの人々には、 チベット人である私も含めて
we don't have this right.
その権利がありません。
Yes, we can live in our country,
確かに、自国で暮らせますが、
but we can't necessarily do what we want to.
したいことが 自由にできるわけではありません。
The day the law
法律が、その権利を
effectively realizes the possibility
すべての人に無条件に保障するという
of granting this right to all people without restriction,
可能性を有効に実現できたら、
on that day humanity will have done more
その日は、人類にとって
than pass over a boundary.
国境を克服した以上の 意味を持ちます。
It will have attained a degree of evolution,
人類の歩んできた発展の道が、
which is desirable
すべての文化と国々にとって
for all cultures and nations.
望ましい水準に 達したといえるでしょう。
It's important...
大切なことです。
that we can live where we want to.
望む場所に住めるということは。
Everyone needs a nest.
だれだって巣が必要です。
Even the birds need a nest.
鳥だって、巣を必要とします。
Human beings need their homes.
人間には住処が必要です。
Question 19, from Claire Mackintosh,
問い19、クレア・マッキントッシュより。
25, Brisbane, Australia.
25歳、 ブリズベン、オーストラリア。
"What are the basic dignities that each human being deserves,"
「人間に与えられるべき 基本的な尊厳とは？
"and why do we let so many people go without them?"
また、多くの人にそれがないことを 我々はなぜ見過ごすのか？」
Basic dignity is human dignity,
基本的な尊厳とは人間の尊厳であり、
their pride, so they can hold their heads up, not down.
誇りであり、そのおかげでうつむくのではなく 顔を上げて堂々と生きられるのです。
They don't have to be scared.
何も恐れることはありません。
Maybe they live in a remote village.
たとえ、どこかの発展途上国の
In some part of a developing country. So what?
片田舎に暮らしていたって いいじゃないですか。
They should be standing straight...
堂々としていられれば...
We let so many people go without them,
それを持たない人々を そのままにしておくから、
so we can let other people do what they do.
別の人々が彼らに 勝手なことをしてしまうんです。
Take lands.
土地を奪う。
Drop bombs.
爆弾を落とす。
Take water.
水を奪う。
Control minds.
思考を支配する。
All for ourselves and nothing for other people
すべては私たちのため、 他者には何もなし。
seems to have been, in every age of the world,
このことは世界のいつの時代においても、
the vile maxim of the masters of mankind.
人類の主人が常に優先してきた やり方なのです。
All for ourselves and nothing for other people.
すべては私たちのため、 他者には何もなし。
It's Adam Smith who said that, Adam Smith, the father of capitalism.
これは、資本主義の父である アダム・スミスの言葉です。
He knew that was the tendency.
彼はこの傾向がわかっていました。
All for ourselves and nothing for other people.
「すべては私たちのため、 他者には何もなし」
The Universal Declaration of Human Rights
世界人権宣言で謳われる言葉は
is what should be available
世界中の人に
for people throughout the world.
共通するはず。
We should not accept that anyone is denied those basic human rights,
基本的人権が否定されることを 私たちは見過ごしてはいけないわ。
the basic human right to live a decent life,
まっとうな生活を送るための 基本的人権、
to have access
生活に不可欠な
to food, shelter and education.
食糧、住居そして教育。
It is unacceptable that in today's world,
今日の世界で許されざるは
there are children dying of hunger.
餓死する子供たちが存在すること。
there are children who have no shelter.
住居のない子供たちが存在すること。
To prepare myself for this question, I used the Internet, Wikipedia,
この問いに答える準備として ウィキペディアを調べ、
and I re-read the United Nations Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
世界人権宣言を読み直したんだ。
and it made me cry.
涙が出たね。
I just wept. It is so beautiful.
泣かずにいられなかった。 すばらしくて。
Let's put it in every passport.
すべてのパスポートに 記すべきだと思う。
My father was exterminated at the age of 37,
私の父は37歳のときに殺され、
my mother at the same age.
母も同じ年で殺されました。
My sisters were exterminated
私の姉妹が殺されたのは
at the age of fourteen and six and twelve and sixteen.
それぞれ 14歳、6歳、12歳と16歳のときでした。
I survived, and life has become very precious for me.
生き延びた私にとって、 命は貴重な意味を持ちました。
And I assume it is also precious for every human being on this planet.
そして、地球上のすべての人間にとって 貴重であるはずです。
And yet it is often taken away for the wrong reasons.
なのに、まちがった理由から 命が奪われていきます。
We teach our children that our lives are worth more than other people's.
私たちは、子供に自分たちの命の方が、 他者よりも価値が高いと教える。
Outsiders, people with a different colour skin,
アウトサイダー、皮膚の色が違う人、
people that have less than we do, people that don't speak our language.
我々よりも所有が少ない人、 我々の言葉を話さない人よりも。
People...
人々...
The other. The other people.
他の。 他の人々。
What happens oftentimes is that those people
よくありがちなのは、 そういう人々が
are really seen as "them" and not "us",
「彼ら」と呼ばれ、 「我々」とみなされないこと。
and there's not much attention paid to or much concern for
すると、 そうした人々の人権や尊厳について
the basic rights and dignities of those people.
私たちはあまり関心をもたないし、 心配もしない。
But I think you have to think about what "we" means in this question.
この問いにおける「我々」について 考えなければなりません。
Who are "we" and who are "they"?
「我々」そして「彼ら」とは だれを指すのでしょうか？
Babies, when they cry, you cannot distinguish
赤ちゃんの泣き声をきくとき、
whether it's a boy, a girl, what their nationality is,
その子が男なのか、女なのか、 国籍も、
or what the mother's religion is.
その子の母親の宗教もわかりません。
It's only one voice.
ただ、声あるのみです。
Don't forget. It's only one sound. We must remember this.
忘れてはならない。声あるのみ。 このことを覚えておくべきです。
I guess if people really saw each other as their brother,
人間が互いを真に兄弟とみなし、
and could imagine that each person out there
そこにいる相手をみな
was their child or relative, it would be really different.
わが子、あるいは親類だと思えたら、 大いに変わるでしょう。
If we could really open our hearts that wide.
我々が心をそこまで大きく開けたら。
Everyone can gain
だれもが自らの尊厳を
human dignity for themselves.
確立できるのです。
Before this, though, one must leave behind
しかし、その前に 取り払わねばならないのは、
the self-imposed oppression of politics, ideology, religion,
自らを束縛する 政治、思想、宗教や
and nationalistic narrow-mindedness.
国家主義的な偏狭さです。
I come...
私は...
I come from the jungle,
私はジャングルからきました。
where I lived most of my life with tribes,
人生のほとんどを 現地の部族と過ごしました。
and where
そこでは
the question of freedom
自由というものが
is much more meaningful than it is here.
ここでよりも 重い意味を持っています。
I've never known any beings that are more free than they are,
彼らほど自由な人間を 私はほかに知りませんね。
the indigenous people.
あの原住民ほど。
No, I never have.
いいえ、決して。
Do you believe this project can change something?
このプロジェクトが なにかを変えられると思いますか？
I knew it from the moment that this murmur first began,
このささやき声、 しゃべり声が聞こえだしたとき、
and this babble of voices.
はっとしたね。
It sent a shiver down my spine,
背中がぞくっとして、
and I realized that something will come of this.
これはなにかを動かしている、って わかった。
I was reminded a little of "Wings of Desire".
「ベルリン・天使の詩」を思い出したよ。
There are these angels which hear all these voices.
あのなかで、天使が やはりそうした声を聞くでしょ。
There's a similar kind of murmur the whole time.
ずっと、これと同じような 声がきこえているんだ。
I could hear this same murmur here, only it was real.
ここでもそれと同じ声がきこえた、 ただし今度は本物だけど。
All these people were actually thinking aloud.
この人たちは 声に出して考えている。
Oh, hey! Did you see Bianca? I think she's over there.
あ！　ビアンカに会ったかい？ あそこにいるはずだよ。
There she is.
ほら、あそこにいるよ。
I think she showed up late.
きっと、遅れたんじゃないかな。
Can you do me a big favour?
ちょっとお願いしてもいいかしら？
Don't move it when I'm talking, because that immediately...
話している最中にカメラを 動かさないでほしいの、じゃないと...
Could you do it before or after or when I stop talking,
前か後なら動かしてもいいの、 あるいは話し終わったとき。
because if you do it when I'm talking my concentration...
話している間に動かされると、 話す集中力が…
-I do it when I get notes from others. -Sure.
-では合図があれば、します。 -了解。
Question 28 from Andrew,
問い28、 アンドリューから。
22, Frankfurt, Germany.
22歳、フランクフルト、ドイツ。
"What if all Chinese people want a car?"
「中国人が全員、 自動車をほしがったら？」
Please begin.
どうぞ、始めて下さい。
This question is a bit racist.
この問いは差別的だわ。
Why not?
それのどこがいけないの？
Everybody needs a car.
だれだって、自動車が必要でしょ。
Why do you only talk about the Chinese?
なぜ、中国人のことだけをいうの？
If you go to America, every family has more than three cars.
アメリカへいってごらん、 一家族が3台以上持ってるわ。
Why Chinese? Everybody wants a car.
なぜ中国人？みんな、車がほしいさ。
Italian, French and German people that don't have a car, want a car.
イタリア人もフランス人もドイツ人も、 車がなければほしいに決まっている。
What if all Indians want a car?
インド人がみんな 車をほしがったらどう？
What if all Africans want a car?
アフリカ人がほしがったら？
If all Chinese people wanted to have a car,
すべての中国人が自動車をほしがって、
and assuming that they would want to drive
しかも、乗りたい車が
the biggest, fastest and most powerful cars,
一番、大きくて、速くて パワフルな車種だとすると、
then the skies above us would darken.
見上げる空が暗くなるだろうね。
Not enough roads, many accidents,
道路が足りず、事故が増え、
not enough car parking space,
駐車場が足りず、
too much pollution.
公害が進みます。
What if all Chinese people want a car?
中国人がみんな自動車をほしがったら？
Then all German people
そうしたら、ドイツ人はみんな
must be turned into automobile workers
自動車製造の労働者になって、
to produce cars for the Chinese until all the Germans are exhausted.
中国人のために車を作らなきゃいけない、 くたびれ果てるまで。
It's an impossible story.
あり得ないね。
The car of today in the wealthy world
豊かな国の自動車は
utilizes 2 to 3 percent of the energy in the gas tank
ガソリンの二、三パーセントをつかって
to actually move the driver.
運転手を移動させます。
The rest is lost in moving the weight of the frame,
残りは、 車両とエンジンの重量を動かす際に、
and the weight of the engine, lost in heat and friction.
そして、熱と摩擦で失われます。
We've devised an enormously sophisticated set
私たちは、一連の非常に洗練された、
of very badly designed vehicles.
非常に悪い仕組みの車を考案しました。
Just to move one person from one place to another.
たった一人の人間を移動させるために。
Petroleum prices will continue their sharp upward movement.
石油の価格は、 依然として高騰し続けます。
And economic chaos in the West, at the most,
下手をすれば西洋で 経済の混乱が起きるか、
or, at the very least, the grim, inevitable realization
少なくとも、苦く、 必然的な認識に到達することでしょう。
that something has to be done
米国を初め西洋諸国での
about the excess consumption of fossil fuels
化石燃料の過剰な消費を
in the United States of America and other Western countries
なんとかしなければならない、 という切迫した思いが、
will be impressed upon people's consciousness.
人々の意識を占めるでしょう。
China, for a long time,
中国は長い間、
was a nation of bicycles.
自転車の国でした。
I'm encouraged that Chinese automakers
僕が期待するのは、 中国の自動車メーカーが
are looking at the ecological impacts of the cars
車が及ぼす環境への影響を考え、
and working very hard at thinking about electric cars.
電気自動車の分野に力を注ぐこと。
China has a huge opportunity,
中国は大きなチャンスがあると同時に、
and a huge responsibility
大きな責任を担っています。
to industrialize in a way that works for its people,
産業化をいかにうまく進めるか。人々、
and for its environment,
環境、
and for the world.
そして世界のために。
What's behind the question is not so much the Chinese people,
この問いは中国人が、という話ではなく
but a metaphor for a situation, which is clearly unsustainable.
持続可能ではない状態の比喩ですね。
We cannot ask of them
ましてや他者に向かって、
what we're not prepared to do ourselves.
私たち自身がやるつもりのないことを 求められないわ。
What we need to do is learn from our mistakes,
私たちがすべきことは、 失敗から学ぶこと。
from the way we've lived, from irrational and irresponsible ways
いかに身勝手で 無責任に生きてきたか、という
in which we have lived our life.
その失敗。
The problem is not how many people want a car,
問題はどれだけの人が 車をほしいか、ではなくて
but that the door to human desires
人間の欲望の扉が
has been opened interminably.
不可逆的に開けられてしまったことだ。
How can we close the door again
この扉をどうやって閉じることができよう、
after opening it to our infinite, possessive desires?
無限の所有欲があふれ出てしまったのに？
-Everything okay? -Everything okay.
-だいじょうぶ？ -だいじょうぶさ。
-How you doing? -Good. A little bit exhausted.
-調子はどう？ -いいよ、ちょっと疲れたけど。
-That's too much? -Yeah.
-けっこう多いね。 -そうだね。
This is just so cool to be here doing this.
ここで、こうしていることが すばらしいね。
-Is it? -The Nazis burned the books here.
-そう？ -この場所でナチスが本を燃やしたんだ。
Oh, now I get it. That stack of books is there because of that.
そうか、それでわかった。だからあそこに 本が積み上げられているのね。
Jesus, I didn't realize that...
まったく、今頃気づくなんて。
Willem. How many questions do you have left?
ウィレム。 あといくつ、問いが残っているんだい？
-After all these questions. -You want to know?
-あれだけ出た後で。 -知りたい？
I'm speaking so much about all the problems.
私、すべての問題について ついたくさん話してしまうの。
I'm setting it all on fire!
ぜんぶ炎上させちゃうのよ！
-Am I doing okay? -Question 33...
-こんな感じでいいかい？ -問い33。
is from the New York-based novelist,
ニューヨーク在住の作家、
Siri Hustvedt, who asks...
シリ・ハストヴェットからの質問です。
I'm very curious to know, to find out,
私がとても興味をそそられるのは、
how consumer culture
現在の消費文化が
actually influences
どんなふうに影響を及ぼすかということ。
the personalities, the ways people live,
例えば人間の個性だとか、生活様式とか
the way they think,
考え方だとか、
inside themselves, in a given culture.
既存の文化における人々の内面に。
How it becomes part of us,
どんな風に私たちの一部となり、
and what it means to be able to resist
そうした言葉と映像の文化に対して
that visual and verbal culture, it seems to me...
抵抗するのはどんな意味があるのか。
"It seems to me, it's always reducing"
「私の感覚では、常に、 現実が還元され、単純化されて」
"and simplifying reality into something"
「なにかの形に成り代わり」
"that can be easily bought and sold."
「簡単に売買できるように なっていると思います。」
I think...
思うに...
Consumer culture...
消費文化は...
It functions to keep creating
その機能は、
a desire in the society, in the community,
社会の欲望を生み出し続け、
that there is something new, something better, more useful...
常になにか新しい物、 よりいい物、より便利な物を...
Man needs nothing.
人間は、何も要らない。
He needs only himself.
自分自身があればいいの。
He needs love.
それから、愛ね。
There are enough coffee pots in the world.
世の中、コーヒーポットは充分あります。
We're surrounded by enough gadgets. There are enough chairs.
たくさんの道具に囲まれ、 いすも充分あります。
Use one of the many hundreds that are already there,
たくさんあるなかからひとつだけ使い、
and then put your extra energy into developing things that really matter.
そのあまったエネルギーを 本当に大切なことに注ぐのです。
All this forms part of a culture of prostitution.
すべては売春文化の一部でしかない。
Our values have become prostituted,
人間の価値が売られ、
and humanity is just a big prostitution machine.
人間性だって、巨大な売春マシンだ。
We created monsters,
我々は怪物をつくってしまった。
monsters of agricultural development.
農業の進歩から生まれた怪物だ。
McDonald's cows are killed and there's no ceremony of killing the animal.
マクドナルドの牛は なんの儀式もなく殺される。
There's no honouring, no thanking the animal for providing food for us.
動物が食を与えてくれることに対し、 なんの敬意も、感謝もない。
So when there's no ceremony, the food we eat becomes bad.
そんな儀式のない食は、悪しき食となる。
And guess what?
それに、知っていますか？
Where McDonald's is eaten
マクドナルドが食されるところでは、
people become sick.
人々が病気になる。
What do you expect? There's no ceremony.
当然じゃないか？儀式もないのだから。
The most powerful people on the face of the planet
世界でもっとも力のある人間とは、
are the ones who can affect the most minds, who...
人々の考え方に影響を与えられる人。
who can influence human behaviour,
人の行いや、社会運動に
and social movements,
影響を与えられる人。
and the way in which societies view themselves,
ほかには社会が自己を見る目、
the way they walk, the way they talk, things they eat, they drink and so on.
歩き方、話し方、食べ方、 飲み方、などへの影響力。
It's all a matter of economics.
結局ぜんぶ、経済の話だ。
It's a model that is destroying us.
私たちを破壊するシステムよ。
It's a model that is consuming us.
私たちを消費するシステム。
What we really need to look at
見つめるべきなのは、
is the free market itself,
自由市場そのものであって、
and see how we can really bring in
私たちがいかにして
the whole aspect of ethics.
道徳的な側面を配慮できるか、 ということ。
Wealth in order to share, to care,
豊かさは分かち合い、相手を思いやり、
and to live happily with oneself and others.
自分自身も他人も幸せに暮らすためのもの。
And the deepest, the best wealth, is how to serve others.
一番深い、よき豊かさとは、 他者に奉仕するためのもの。
Question 37
問い 37。
is from Tom Henze, 30, Berlin, Germany.
トム・ヘンツェ、 30歳、ベルリン、ドイツ。
"Does our wealth depend on the Third World being poor?"
「私たちの富は、第三世界の貧困の上に 成り立っているのか？」
The expression "Third World" is truly an arrogant claim.
「第三世界」と呼ぶこと自体、傲慢だ。
It is not a Third World, it's just a world
第三世界じゃない。単に、
that has developed differently or hasn't developed as fast.
発展のしかたが異なるか、 発展がゆっくりな世界だというだけ。
But it is not the Third World. What's the First World then?
だが、第三世界じゃない。 第一はどこになる？
What is that definition of the Third World anyway?
第三世界とは どのように定義されるんだ？
Is there a First World, a Second World and a Third World?
第一、第二、第三の世界があるかい？
Not really.
ないだろ。
One world?
ひとつの世界？
Not doing so well? Humans fucking it up?
うまくいっていない？ 人間が台無しにしている？
I mean, if our wealth depends on the Third World being poor,
我々の豊かさが 第三世界の貧困のおかげだとしたら、
then we're in trouble, we're in trouble...
それは問題だ。本当に問題だ。
They started by taking the gold away.
彼らはまず、金を奪ったのよ。
But for indigenous people
でも、先住民にとって
gold didn't have the same value as it did for capitalists.
金は、資本主義者たちとは 同じ意味を持っていなかった。
Africa has been the cradle of mankind,
アフリカは人類のゆりかごだといいますが、
and I stand very clearly on this, and say that Africa
私があえてはっきりといいたいのは、
is also going to be the deathbed of capitalism.
アフリカが、資本主義の 臨終の床になるということです。
Oh plundered Africa...
略奪されたアフリカ...
Africa, terrible Africa.
アフリカ、悲惨なアフリカ。
It's impossible to talk about Africa without feeling...
アフリカについて話すとき、 感情なくしては話せない。
without feeling our hearts twinge.
胸を引き裂かれるような思いでしか。
Those who are well-fed never understand
満腹に暮らしている人には、決して
what it feels like to be hungry.
餓えの苦しみはわからない。
A Nigerian chief said:
ナイジェリアの酋長がこういったんです。
"If you won't share your wealth, we'll share our poverty with you."
「その富を我々と分かち合わないなら、 我々の貧困を分けてやろうじゃないか」
If you want global peace, we have to talk about equitable distribution.
世界平和を望むなら、 公平な分配について考えることです。
We also have to understand that all of the resources
納得すべきなのは、 資源をみんなで分かち合う、
are shared by all and they are, first of all, for those in need.
だけど、まずは必要な人々に 与えるべきだということ。
Real property is property by need. It comes about through need.
真の所有は、必要性のある所有です。 必要から生じるのです。
When I need a glass of water, then it is mine by right of need.
グラス一杯の水がほしいとき、 必要性に基づいて僕のものとなるのです。
Fair... "Fair" is not a word
公平... 「公平」という言葉は
that you hear in economics too much.
経済ではあまりきかない言葉だね。
There is a connection that we have to make
つながりを作る必要があります。
as to the poverty of the people,
人々の貧困と、
the wealth of the land, and be observant as to
その国の富との間に。 そして監視するのです、
where this wealth is going.
どこへ富が行ってしまうのか。
What I believe globalization is really about
私の考えるグローバル化とは、
is forming global family, moving out of what I call
グローバルな家族を作ることです。 その際には、
a juvenile species mode of hostile competition,
未熟さの表れである 敵対的な競争関係から抜け出し、
and into a more mature mode of cooperation.
もっと成熟した 協力関係へと移行するのです。
This has happened to many species all through evolution
これは、進化の間に多くの品種が やり遂げたことですから
and it's our turn now as humans to do this.
今度は私たち人間がそうする番です。
I make it very simple.
簡単にいいましょう。
One is joining in the generosity of the divine,
人が、神的な寛大さに組したいと思えば、
which is a power of giving.
与える力を得る。
All life is given to us.
命すべてが与えられる。
And those who do that are "for giving".
また、そうする人は「与える」派です。
And if your life is centred around getting,
でも、もし君の生活が 取ることを中心に回っていたら、
then you're joining in the culture of "for getting".
君は「取る」文化の一部ということになる。
So the choice is to be part of "for getting" and being forgotten,
選択肢は「取る」の一部となって 忘れられるか、
or part of "for giving" and being forgiven.
あるいは「与える」の一部となって 許されるか、だ。
I like that! That's great.
それ、すごくいいですね。 すばらしいわ。
-He said it for me, my neighbour. -Repeat. Repeat.
-隣の方がいって下さったわ。 -もう一度、繰り返して。
Yes. Can you come and sit in my seat and say it for me?
ええ。私の席にかけて、 私の代わりにいって下さる？
I would like it if we had more interaction in this process.
お互いにもっとやり取りがあるといいよね。
I'm enlivened by sharing with somebody.
だれかと分かち合うと、 元気が出てくるから。
My brain doesn't, my brain doesn't... I mean, this! Talking to you...
でも私の脳が、脳があまり... これはね、君にいってるんだよ！君に...
Talking to you!
君に向けた言葉なんだ！
-Hi, sweetheart. Hi! How are you?
-あら、こんにちは。 ‐あれ、どう調子は？
Are you having fun, baby?
楽しんでるかしら？
-Are you having fun? -Yeah.
-楽しんでる？ -ええ。
Because you're so smart. You're such a genius.
あなた、賢いから。天才的よ。
Answers just roll off your tongue.
答えがすらすらと口をついて出てくる。
-I don't know, I don't know. -I don't know!
-わからない、わからない。 -わからないよ！
We're part of a big experiment.
ぼくら、大実験中なんだろ？
It's not about the questions. This is about us.
問いがどうのというより ぼくら自身のことなんだ。
Go ahead.
どうぞ、続けて。
Thank you.
どうもありがとう。
While you were giving your answers to that last question,
さっきの最後の問いに みなさんが答えている間、
I walked through the circle and could see all your faces, hear your voices,
私は輪のなかを歩きながら、 みなさんの顔や声、
see your expressions.
表情を見ることができました。
And it was deeply moving for me to see
とても感動的でした、
everything that I saw as I walked through the circle.
輪を歩きながら 目に入ったすべてのことが。
It's such a diverse group that we have here.
これだけ多様な人々の 集まりなのですから！
We're our own United Nations!
私たち自身による国連です！
I saw people from Africa, from Asia, Australia,
アフリカ、アジア、オーストラリア、
from Europe and the Americas.
ヨーロッパ、そしてアメリカからの方々。
It's beautiful that we're all here investing in the future.
将来への投資をしに、 ここに集まったのはすばらしいことです。
Question 41.
問い  41。
From Adrienn Meszaros, 30, Budapest, Hungary.
アドリエン・メッサロス、 30歳、ブダペスト、ハンガリーより。
"Is there a modern version of colonialism?"
「植民地主義の 新しい形態は存在しますか？」
Yes.
はい。
There is a modern version of colonialism.
植民地主義の現代版は存在します。
And it's called debt.
それは、借金と呼ばれています。
It is called debt,
借金と呼ばれ、
followed by the structural adjustment policies
構造調整政策というものを、
imposed by the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund.
世界銀行と世界通貨基金から 押し付けられます。
A lot of this money coming to developing countries
たくさんのお金が発展途上国に流れ、
is used to control the sovereignty of our own governments,
私たちの政府の主権、国民の主権を
of our own people...
操るために使われます。
The Bank and the Fund say, if you're going to pay back your debt,
世界銀行と通貨基金がいうには、 借金を返すなら、
and you must pay back your debt,
借金は返さないといけないから、
then you have to put interest rates way up...
お宅の国の利子率を 上げなければなりません。
That makes it harder for businesses to borrow and to employ people.
それが、事業の資金繰りや 雇用を国内で困難にしているのです。
You've got to privatize everything in sight,
何もかも 民営化しなくてはならないその国では、
so that gives big opportunities
その大きなチャンスにすかさず
to foreign companies and local elites
外国企業や現地のエリートが
to buy up all of the previously public companies.
かつての公営会社を 買い上げてしまいます。
The United States of America was itself built
アメリカ合衆国は、
on the decimation of an entire people.
ある民族の抹殺の上に成り立っている。
Europe has been built
ヨーロッパは、
on sucking out the Congo,
コンゴを搾取し、
on sucking out the gold and diamonds of South Africa.
南アフリカの金やダイアモンドを 搾取した上に成り立っている。
Slavery was about the exploitation of raw materials.
奴隷化は、資源を奪うためだった。
Today it's about oil.
今では石油、そしてダイアモンドだ。
Today it's about diamonds, minerals and primary resources.
今ではダイアモンド、鉱物、 そして一次資源。
The countries...
国々は...
the Latin American countries,
ラテン・アメリカの国々は、
continue to suffer exploitation,
いまだに搾取され続けています。
the exploitation of their resources.
資源の搾取。
All of these policies have been very beneficial
こうした政治は、 利益をもたらしました、
to a tiny minority of the people in these countries.
その国々のほんの一握りの人に。
Just like vampires. They are vampires!
吸血鬼みたい。吸血鬼なのよ！
They use the energy, the strength and the lives of others,
彼らは、他人の力、強さ、命をつかって
for their own economic prosperity.
自分の経済を潤すの。
It's modern economic colonialism based on globalization,
グローバル化に基づいた 現代の経済植民地主義です。
but its structure is almost exactly the same
しかし、構造的には
as it has been for four or five hundred years.
四、五百年前とまったく同じ。
It's better than colonialism, because it doesn't need an army.
植民地主義よりも巧妙です、 軍隊が要らないのだから。
It doesn't need an administration.
管理する組織もいりません。
It doesn't cost you anything, the state, the powers intervening...
なんの代償も払わなくていい、 国家、干渉する権力。
"We are children of a world that has enough for everyone."
「私たちは、 すべてのために充分ある地球の子供です。
"But so many remain hungry, while so few are well fed."
でも、多くが飢えていて、 満たされているのはほんの少し。
"One will eat, the other suffers."
一人が食べると、他が苦しむ。
"This is how it's always been."
これまでもずっとそうだった。
"Other nations must be poor, so that rich ones can be rich."
他の国は貧しいままでいい、 豊かな国が豊かであるために。」
And this is a really ideal system,
これが理想的な制度だというのは、
because it isn't even very visible.
目には見えないからです。
Colonialism is visible.
植民地主義は目に見えます。
People think this is rotten. Those pictures taken.
その写真を見て、不快になります。
But debt is invisible, and it works just as well, even more efficiently.
でも、借金は見えない上に、 同様に機能し、もっと能率がいいくらい。
I don't like to be sitting here as an American talking about this,
アメリカ人としてここで この話をするのは居心地悪いものです。
but this is the underbelly of the real world that we live in.
でも、それが現実世界の 暗い側面なのです。
It's very real. It has caused enormous misery,
限りなく現実です。 そして多くの困窮をもたらしました。
and we have to know what's going on in our world
私たちは世界で起こっていることを 知らなければなりません、
in order to change it.
その状況を変えるために。
There must be some democratic forms of life
もっと違ったかたちでの 民主主義的な生き方、
and forms of organization
組織のあり方があるはずだ、
that can sidestep all imperial
それが、どんな帝国主義的、
and colonial forms of subjugation.
植民地主義的な服従を免れるように。
That's the great question of the 21st Century.
これは、21世紀の重大な問いだ。
Question 45 from Katharina, 24, Germany.
問い 45。 カタリナより、24歳、ドイツ。
"Why do we still believe more in nationality than in humanity?"
「私たちはなぜ、いまだに人間性よりも、 国籍を信用するのか？」
It is by the conditioning of mind that we are
それは我々の脳の状態が、
trained, trained, trained all the time,
ずっと訓練され続けた結果、
that we are part of a national identity.
国のアイデンティティの 一部になってしまうからだ。
That is how we see it.
そういう視点になる。
And, within a nation, again it gets down to
そして、その国の中でも今度は
smaller and smaller and smaller identities...
もっともっと小さなグループの アイデンティティがある。
And so we are fearful.
だから私たちは恐れるのです。
We have been put into a framework to protect ourselves.
自分たちを守るために、 枠の中に入れられています。
We're so insecure.
不安を抱いています。
We do not know who is for us, and who is not for us,
だれが味方で、 だれが敵なのかわかりません。
and that has destroyed humanity.
それが人間性を破壊したのです。
Let me give you an example.
ひとつ、例を挙げましょう。
In Iraq now, my country Iraq,
いま、私の国、イラクでは
most people cling to
ほとんどの人がしがみつき、
and trust
信じるのは
only their own people,
自分たちだけ、
or their neighbours, or others from their city.
あるいは隣人や同じ町の人。
Before, we did not ask who a person was,
それまでは、相手がだれなのか、
where they came from, from which city,
どこの町から来たのか、
from which tribe or family.
どの民族や家系に属するのか いちいち尋ねませんでした。
We would be friendly, that's all.
ただ、相手を 友好的に迎え入れていたのです。
It is security, psychological security,
でも安全性、 心理的な安心感によって
that enables people to feel an expanded sense of self,
人間は自分というものの 価値観が広がり、
that enables them to respect difference.
他者との違いを 尊重できるようになるのです。
It is when people feel frightened, scared, cut off,
でも人間が恐れ、怯え、孤立すると
that intolerance grows,
どんどん寛容ではなくなるのです。
and in the nation states today people are being manipulated
そして国家のなかで 人々はマスコミによって
through the mass media
扇動され、
to learn to hate the other, whom they have never met.
会ったこともない、よその人々を 憎むように刷り込まれるのです。
We live in a world, where we have been conditioned
我々は、なんらかの属性を持つよう 条件付けられています。
to be tribal, to be nativist,
ある民族の一員として、 保護主義者として
to be nationalist.
あるいはナショナリストとして。
Of course, it's important to understand
もちろん 理解していなければならないのは
that nationalism is really fanaticism.
ナショナリズムが 真に狂信的だということ。
I believe that within each of us
おそらく、すべての人に
there is a racist dictator.
人種差別主義的な独裁者が 潜んでいるでしょう。
I'm convinced of this.
そう確信しています。
Because we are closer to the family than we are to the clan,
私たちにとって家族が親族よりも近く
closer to the clan than to the tribe,
親族のほうが部族よりも近く、
closer to the tribe than to the nation,
部族のほうが国民よりも近く、
closer to the nation than to humanity.
国民のほうが人間性よりも 近い存在なのです。
I don't believe in nationality at all,
私は国籍を信用しません。
and I think more and more of us in the 21st Century,
21世紀の自分たちについて考えたとき、
children of the world of possibility, children of the future tense,
可能性の世界の子供、未来の子供は、
live in the passageways between nations, cultures and categories,
もしかしたら国家文化や区分を超えた 中間にいるかもしれない、
outside the traditional definitions.
従来の定義から外れた場所に。
Our affiliations are not to nations,
私たちが所属するのは国家でなく、
or to the traditional order, but to something beyond that.
従来の秩序でもなく、 なにかそれを越えたものだろう。
I believe that, to a certain extent,
僕が思うには、ある程度のところまで、
the concept of nationality is beginning to erode
国家という発想は既に崩れかけていて
as we turn into a kind of genuinely transnational people.
ますます本来の姿に、 国家を超えた人間になっていくのではないか。
Sometimes the worst enemy
時として、最悪の敵は
is our own perception.
自分自身の知覚だ。
Thank you.
ありがとう。
Question 48 from Glen, Cape Town, South Africa.
問い48はグレンからです。 ケープタウン、南アフリカ。
"How do we stop our governments from going to war?"
「どのように自国の政府が 戦争するのを阻止できるか？」
I come from a land where there has never been a war,
私は、 一度も戦争したことのない国からきました。
so I do not know anything about war,
だから、戦争のことは何も知りません。
but I do know of the suffering you people have experienced.
でも、あなた方が戦争で 苦しみを受けたことは知っています。
Me? I come from the land of peace.
私ですか？平和の国からきました。
Where nothing but peace had been in existence.
平和しか知らない国。
Where no one fears being shot.
撃たれる恐れも知らず、
Where no one is aiming at you.
銃口を向けられたこともなく、
Where no one fights for land.
領土のために戦ったこともありません。
We go to war: you, me, us.
戦争に行くのは我々。あなた、私、我々。
Governments don't go to war. Governments send us to war.
政府は戦争に行かない。 政府が我々を戦争に送る。
We pay the price,
我々が代償を払う。
and the price that we pay is not only physical.
支払う代償は 肉体的なものだけでなく、
The price that we pay is psychic.
精神的な代償も払う。
We lose our moral groundedness. We lose ourselves.
モラルの基盤を失い、 自分自身を見失う。
It's really a shame.
実際、恥ずべきことだわ。
The big powers should be ashamed
強国は恥じるべきよ、
of what they are doing with the civilizations. Killing them?
文明へのひどい仕打ちを。殺すつもり？
I'm a survivor of war in Bosnia.
私は、ボズニアの戦争を生き延びました。
For three and a half years of my childhood,
子供時代の3年半の間に
millions of bombs exploded in my city, and...
何百万という爆弾が 私の街で爆発しました。
To hear a bomb explode is an experience
爆弾の爆発音をきくことは
that can't be explained or described,
とても説明できない体験です。
because you feel it in your body.
体内でそれを感じるから。
I remember just my whole body reacting
思い出すのは、私の体が
to such loudness and destruction.
その凄まじい爆破と 破壊の音に反応して
My heart would jump every time, millions of times.
毎回、心臓が跳ね上がりました。 何百万回となく。
There were times when it felt like my heart could no longer take it,
時々、もう私の心臓はこれに耐えられない、
like it would just burst into millions of pieces.
粉々にはじけ散ってしまうかと思いました。
We're nothing but collateral damage. We're not talking about numbers.
私たちは民間の犠牲者です。 数の話をしてるのではありません。
We're not talking about destroyed lives or families.
破壊された生活や家族の話を してるのではありません。
We're talking about collateral damage. It's just numbing.
巻き添えで犠牲者となった民間人。 茫然とさせられます。
Because we're not seeing a face. It is distant.
その顔は見えません。 離れたできごとです。
The political process has lost touch
政治のプロセスは、 現実との接点を失い、
with the reality that war is only about economics.
戦争はいまや 経済的な理由のみで起こる。
It is incomprehensible how, nowadays,
理解しがたいのは、
the world powers
世界の強国が
can spend so much money on death.
莫大なお金を死のためにつかう、 ということだ。
We've lost our connection to
私たちがつながりを なくしてしまったのは、
our responsibility for what our governments do.
政府が行うことへの 私たちの責任です。
And we get lost in our powerlessness,
無力感のなかで 自分自身を見失いながらも、
and we think we can change it in a few moments.
その状態をすぐに変えられると 錯覚しています。
People marched against the war and it didn't work,
戦争反対のデモ行進をしても なにも変わらず、
so everyone goes back to living their lives again,
人々はまた ふだんの生活に戻るんだけど、
while what they went to the streets for has become
その間に、 反対運動をしたはずのことが
a greater nightmare than they could have ever imagined.
想像を超えるような 悪夢のような事態になってしまう。
Why was it so horrible then
デモをした当時ひどかった戦争が
and not so horrible now that no one's in the streets?
デモしなくなったら それほどひどくなくなったのはなぜ？
How you stop the government is a very difficult question.
政府を阻止するのは難しい問題だ。
The only way one could do it is by overthrowing that government,
唯一の方法は 政府を転覆させることだろうね、
by a revolution.
革命を起こして。
But then the notion of revolution in our time is so archaic, so dépassé.
でも革命なんて、 いまどき時代遅れの感がある。
We don't think in those terms anymore,
そんな言葉は思い浮かばない。
but that is the only way to stop a government.
しかし、政府をとめるには それしかないじゃないか。
The most important step
一番重要なステップとして
that all the women of the world can take
世界中の女性ができることは、
is not to give their children away
子供たちを送り出さないことです、
to be turned into soldiers, to be turned into killers.
兵隊や殺人者に 仕立て上げられないために。
I come from a region where we all started to hate each other,
私の国では、みんなが互いを憎み合い、
and to kill each other savagely
残虐な殺し合いをし、
as if the others were no longer human.
相手を人間とも思わないような ことをしていました。
We have these disasters in which, in a very short period of time,
こうした惨劇は、 ほんの短い間に発揮される
a massive amount of destructive power can be brought to bear.
とてつもない破壊力のせいで 引き起こされます。
The governments doing this must be replaced.
こんなことをする政府は 取って代わられねばなりません。
The leaders individually responsible for these actions
こうした戦争行為の 責任を負う各リーダーたちは
must be held to justice.
法で裁かれなくてはなりません。
We've seen a wonderful trend in the past twenty years
ここ20年の間に 喜ばしい進歩がありました。
with General Pinochet and a number of others,
ピノチェト将軍をはじめとする 何人もの軍人が
whose actions led to genocide, led to disappearances, led to death,
大勢の人々を殺戮し、 死者、行方不明者を出した責任を問われ、
being brought before world courts of justice.
世界の法の裁きを受けたのです。
So we must move to a world in which every leader
だから、だれにでも適用される 世界規範が必要です。
is held accountable in the same way,
どのリーダーも同じように責任を問われ、
with the feeling that their actions will be judged.
その行いが裁かれなければなりません。
As a human being I feel that... What is today's war?
人間として思うのは、現代の戦争とは何？
We are killing each other and it's something that
互いに殺しあうことは、
is taking peace away from a lot of people.
たくさんの、たくさんの人から 平和を奪うこと。
Question 56.
問い56。
From Moise Marabout, 23,
モイーズ・マラボー、23歳、
Agadez, Niger.
アガデス、ニジェール。
"Why is there no peace in the Middle East yet?"
「中東にまだ平和が訪れないのはなぜ？」
This question is extremely, extremely, extremely,
この問いは、とても、とても、とても
extremely close to my heart as an Israeli.
胸に迫る問題ですね、 イスラエル人の私としては。
I can only say that, the way I see it,
私の視点からしか語れませんが、
there's no peace in the Middle East,
中東に平和が訪れないのは、
because of the vanity of Israel.
イスラエルのうぬぼれのせいです。
As long as justice is not addressed,
正義と取り組まない限り、
we will not have peace.
平和はありません。
Peace is not a moment between conflicts,
平和とは、紛争の合間の休止状態ではなく、
but a continuous state one lives and strives for.
目指すべき継続的な状態です。
The only peace now
今の平和は、
is false peace,
偽の平和だ。
peace based upon lack of trust.
不信の上に成り立っている平和。
Oil.
石油。
I believe the reason is that there are fanatics on both sides.
双方に狂信者がいる というのが原因だと思います。
On both sides.
双方に。
You can't ignore the fact that we are deeply scarred as a people,
私たちがひどく怯えていることは 事実として、無視できません。
but instead of trying to heal ourselves
でも、自分たち自身を癒すために
by recognizing that we must use compassion,
他人を思いやることを思い出したり、
love and forgiveness,
愛することや、許すこと、
and engage in dialogue eye to eye,
打ち解けた対話の重要性を 考える代わりに
we keep hiding behind our supposed righteousness,
私たちは、仮想の正義の後ろに 隠れ続けるのです。
but there is no such thing.
でも、実際にはありません。
We feel like we can do anything, because of what was done to us.
自分たちにされたことを口実に、 何をしても許されると思っているんです。
I believe Palestinians and Israelis want to be able to coexist together.
パレスチナ人とイスラエル人は 共存を願っていると思うよ。
The whole argument that we were here first
こっちが先に住んでいたとか、
that they were here first, is irrelevant.
あっちが先だとかの論争は この際関係ない。
We are all visitors on this planet.
我々のだれもが、 この地球の訪問者なのだから。
We are all strangers walking on borrowed land.
大地を借りている異邦人なのだから。
Once Palestinians and Israelis live equally with self-respect,
パレスチナ人とイスラエル人が 平等に、尊厳を保ち、
with respect to each other and solidarity,
互いを尊重し、連帯意識を持って暮らせば、
it will echo to the entire world.
世界中から反響がくるだろうね。
It will stop these stupid battles
あの愚かな戦いに終止符を打つ。
of the state deciding between the culture of the West and the Muslims.
西洋文化とイスラム文化との 板ばさみになってくりひろげる戦い。
It's such bullshit. In Israel and Palestine we can prove
なんてバカバカしい。 イスラエルとパレスチナでこそ、
that together this can be the most beautiful culture one can have.
双方が手を結べば、 最高の文化になることを証明できるのに。
I know I sound like a dreamer...
ええ、夢物語にきこえることでしょう。
In my country, in my community, we normally say...
私の国、私の共同体でよくいうんですが...
which means,
その意味は、
"Where two bulls fight, normally the grass is the one that suffers."
「二頭の雄牛が闘うと、 痛むのは地面の草。」
Question 61 from Wolfgang Jost,
問い61はヴォルフガング・ヨスト、
23, Berlin, Germany...
23歳、ベルリン、ドイツから。
"Why is an Iranian nuclear bomb"
「イランの核爆弾は、
"supposed to be more dangerous than an American, Israeli or French?"
なぜ、米国やイスラエルやフランスのより 危険とみなされるのか？」
Let us not ask this question in America or France or in Israel.
これは、米国やフランス、 イスラエルで発するべき質問じゃないね。
But let us ask this question
だが、この質問を
in Algeria or in Iraq,
アルジェリアやイラク、
or in Lebanon or in Palestine...
レバノンやパレスチナ、あるいは...
Or even Japan!
日本でしたらどうだろう？
August 7, 1945.
1945年、8月7日。
America dropped a bomb on Hiroshima.
米国は広島に原爆を投下した。
Some hundred thousand people were killed, school children,
何十万人も死んだ。 学校の子供たち、民間人。
civilians, and the killing went on for years,
殺戮はその後、何年にもわたって
because of the atomic consequences.
被爆の影響で続いた。
Who has really been using those bombs, practically?
原爆を実際に使用したのはだれだった？
Until now, just the USA.
今のところ、米国だけだ。
Iran pledges, promises, to destroy Israel.
イランはイスラエルを破壊することを 予告し、約束する。
And there is no doubt that if Iran were to have a nuclear bomb,
確実なのは、イランが核兵器を得たとき、
it would keep its promise.
必ずその約束を果たすだろう、ということ。
Israel? Israel's bombs?
イスラエル。イスラエルの爆弾？
Where do they come from?
どこから来るんだろうね？
We make those.
我々が作っているんだよ。
We sell them to Israel.
我々がイスラエルに売ってるってわけ。
The American, Israeli and French bombs should be eliminated.
米国、イスラエルとフランスの爆弾は なくすべき。
France and the United States have a legal obligation to do so
フランスと米国は法的に そうする義務がある、
under the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty.
核拡散防止条約に基づいて。
And Israel has a security interest
そしてイスラエルは安全保障上、
in really resolving the conflicts in its region through non-violent means.
その地域の紛争を 武力行使せずに解決することを望んでいる。
As long as some have nuclear weapons others will want them.
だれかが核兵器を保有する限り、 他の国も保有したがる。
As long as they want them, they'll get them.
ほしいと願い続ければ、 いつか手にしてしまう。
And as long as they exist, it's inevitable
そんな爆弾が存在する限り、 避けられないのは
that either through accident or design, they will be used.
事故、あるいは意図的に それが使用されてしまうこと。
Any use is catastrophic, therefore they must be abolished.
いずれにせよ、破滅的だから それはなくさなければならない。
Why do we have to have a nuclear bomb?
なぜ、核爆弾なんか必要なんでしょう？
We shouldn't be... If we were to start all over again,
こんなはずじゃ... もし、最初からやり直せるなら、
no one would say that it was a good idea to build nuclear bombs.
誰一人、核爆弾の開発が いい案だとはいわないでしょう。
Insane!
正気じゃない！
Who would we be if we didn't live in the shadow of the atomic bomb?
もし、原爆の影に怯えずに暮らせたら 私たちはどうしていたかしら？
We would be very different people.
きっと、もっと別な人間に なっていたと思うんです。
Would we live in this sense of fear that is manipulated
外部からかんたんに操られてしまうような
by external powers so easily?
恐れを抱いて、暮らしていた？
Would we still be allowing the level of violence that we allow?
いま許されているような暴力のレベルを 果たして許していたでしょうか？
I don't think so.
していなかったと思います。
I think we could have found some wonderful ways
きっと、もっとすばらしい方法を 見つけていたんじゃないかと思う、
to deal with conflict that wasn't violence.
紛争を武力以外の方法で 解決するために。
And I do think that who we are in the 21st Century
そして、21世紀にいる私たち自身が
has deeply been affected
兵器技術の進歩によって
by the technological advances in weaponry.
多大な影響を受けているはずです。
I don't think we fully understand
まだ完全には理解していないのです、
what that's done to our humanity, what it's done
人間性に対してされた仕打ちが何を変え、
to American citizens to have used the atomic bomb.
原爆を使ったことによって アメリカ人の何を変えてしまったのか。
I think that contributes to how...
それによって、
how violent our own inner nature is.
いかに私たちの内面が暴力的であるか。
It has contributed to the level of depression,
それによって憂鬱の度合い、
the level of addictions,
依存の度合いが決まり、
the disconnect and denial...
分離され、拒絶され。
I think it would be a very different world,
きっと、全然ちがった世界に なっていたはず。
certainly one more caring and generous...
もっと思いやりがあって、寛容で。
Thank you.
ありがとう。
Question 62 is from
問い62は、
the writer and activist Arundhati Roy.
作家であり、活動家の アルンダティ・ロイからです。
"Between non-violent resistance and armed struggle where do we go?"
「非暴力の抵抗と武力による闘い、 どちらにすべき？
"What is effective?" "What is the right thing to do?"
何が効果的？どうするのが正しい？
"Or do we need a biodiversity of resistance?"
あるいは、抵抗の生物多様性が必要？」
Arundhati, if you could sit here and hear this murmur...
アルンダティ、あなたがここにいて このささやき声が聞こえ、
and see all these faces.
この人々の顔を見られたら。
I like the term "biodiversity of resistance".
「抵抗の生物多様性」っていうのがいいね。
This is a great question
これはすごい問いだ。
and I'm not sure if we are the ones to answer it.
でも、ぼくらがこれに答えていい 立場にあるだろうか。
I would prefer to say that I prefer a non-violent resistance.
ぼくは、非暴力の抵抗を、といいたい。
I wish this resistance would make it.
抵抗によって達成されるものと思いたい。
But we are not the ones to choose the resistance of the oppressed.
でも弾圧されている人々に 抵抗の形態を指定なんかできない。
We certainly need a variety of forms of resistance.
抵抗の形態が多様にあるべきなのは、 確かにそのとおり。
Armed struggle must be the last resort,
武力による闘いは 最後の手段であるべきだから。
and something that we are very, very mindful of
そのときは、注意深くなくてはならず、
and oftentimes suspicious of.
なるべく懐疑的でいたほうがいい。
And yet there are conditions under which armed struggle
それでも、 武力がどうしても必要になる場合も
becomes necessary.
あるだろう。
For the most part we must deploy
だが、ほとんどの場合は
all forms of non-violent resistance and struggle,
あらゆる形態の 非暴力の抵抗、闘いを駆使して
understanding non-violence as something active,
非暴力が活動の形態として
as something that's vital and vibrant,
生命と活力に満ち、
something that requires our sacrifice, our suffering,
犠牲と苦しみを 代償とすることを知らしめ、
something that allows us to accent the best in ourselves
自分や他人の内のいちばん善の部分を
and the best in others.
示せるようでなければならない。
The struggle for change
変化のための闘いにおいて
in every single place where struggle has been successful
それが成功したケースはどれも
has employed what you term a "biodiversity" of tactics.
作戦の上で、あなたがいう 「生物多様性」を保持していました。
From non-violent resistance
非暴力の抵抗から、
to political organizing, to speechmaking
政治組織、演説、
to armed struggle.
そして、武力闘争にいたるまで。
Legitimate armed struggle based on the principles laid down by
武力闘争を正当化するために 起草された原則は、
the African National Congress and Che Guevara,
アフリカ民族会議と チェ・ゲバラによるものですが、
to distinguish between mere terrorism,
これは、単なるテロ行為による、 暴力自体を目的化し、
violence for its own sake with unnecessary casualties,
無意味に犠牲者を出す形態とは 一線を画すもの。
and armed struggle that is undertaken to mobilize and protect
その武力闘争は、弾圧されている多数を
an oppressed majority.
動員し、保護するためなのです。
As an organizer, whatever decision I make
組織する一人として、 どんな決定を下そうが、
and whatever movement I'm engaged in, I have to ask myself:
どんな運動のなかにいようが、 常に自問するのは：
Can I live with the impact of the tactic I'm going to use?
選んだ作戦がもたらす結果の 責任を負えるか、ということ。
It never happens that when change is taking place,
変化が起こったとき、あり得ないのは
that it does not affect others.
だれも余波を受けない、ということです。
There are always victims of change.
変化には、必ず犠牲が付きまといます。
Ask yourself: How much are you willing to give?
まず考えましょう。 どれほどの覚悟がありますか？
How convinced are you of your goal?
目的に迷いはありませんか？
And then you can choose the weapons.
では、武器を選びましょう。
It could be a pen, it could be a gun,
ペンでもいいし、銃でもいい。
it could be a camera, it could be a piece of paper, it could be a knife,
カメラでも、紙切れでも、ナイフでもいい、
it could be your life.
あなたの命でもいい。
We can accomplish a lot with non-violent resistance.
非暴力の抵抗で 多くを達せられると思います。
But are there times when armed struggles are justified?
でも、武力闘争は 正当化できるでしょうか？
Are revolutions justified?
革命は正当化される？
Concentrating on resistance, there's something wrong with that.
抵抗にばかり目を向けるのは 誤っているんじゃないかしら。
We're not just concentrating on resistance.
抵抗することばかりに 集中していてはいけません。
We have to create "attractance".
魅力ある代案を練らないといけません。
We have to create a new paradigm, which is attractive to go to.
新しく、達成し甲斐のある 魅力的な範型。
If everyone were to bloom in their own beauty... Imagine that!
だれもが、それぞれの美しさで 輝いていたら...想像してごらん！
Everyone sitting in a circle at this table blooming in their own beauty.
ここに座っている全員が それぞれの美しさで輝いているんだ。
Yes, Arundhati,
そうです、アルンダティ、
we need biodiversity on Earth.
この地球には、生物多様性が必要です。
It's everyone's language, everyone's culture,
みんなの言語であり、みんなの文化であり、
everyone's spiritual understanding.
みんなの精神的理解です。
At this very moment, you can see around me
この瞬間、周りを見回すと
a circle that represents a global community
グローバルなコミュニティを 代表する輪として、
where there is diversity, diversity of thought,
多様性がある。考えの多様性、
diversity of ideas, diversity of concepts.
発想の多様性、コンセプトの多様性。
Is anyone there listening to us?
だれか、 これを聞いている人はいるんですか？
At any time?
いつでも？
It will probably be catapulted into the world
きっと、世界に向けて 飛び出していくだろうね、
like a discus.
円盤みたいに。
Great.
すごいね。
Yes? Does that sound good? Oh good.
そう？いいと思う？ よかった。
Can you take your head off?
ちょっと頭を一休みさせて、
So you can really feel what's going on around you,
周りで起こっていることを 純粋に感じたらどうかな。
sense what's going on around you.
周りのことを、感覚だけで。
Or are you still in your mind, thinking?
それとも、まだ考えちゃっている？
-Our friend the camera. -Guys!
-カメラは友達ね。 -おい、みんな。
Whatever you hear from me, if there is one smart thing,
ぼくが話したなかで、 ひとつでも賢いこといってたら
take it and the rest please erase it...
それだけとって、あとはぜんぶ消してね。
You also went to the centre. How was the centre?
輪の真ん中に行ったのね。 真ん中はどうだった？
It was really good. It's amazing. You can click onto the different...
すごくいい。びっくりするよ。 いろんなのをクリックできて。
You can go to any camera.
どのカメラにもいけるんだ。
Question 75.
問い75。
From Sara Francis, 35, Dublin, Ireland.
サラ・フランシスより。 35歳、ダブリン、アイルランド。
"What does courage mean now?"
「勇気とは今日、何を意味するか？」
"Courage is something I appreciate so much in a person."
勇気とは、私がその人物に 一目をおく部分です。
"I salute people who have courage."
勇気ある人々に敬服します。
"Courage helps you to continue to live your day-to-day life."
勇気は、 日々の暮らしを続けるのを助けてくれます。
"Courage is something... Step by step, you go up!"
「勇気は、一歩一歩、 段を上っていくようなもの！」
It takes courage to be a human being. It takes courage to be!
人間であるには、勇気が要る。 存在するには、勇気が要る。
Solitude is courage. Hermetics. Total neutrality.
孤独は勇気だ。孤立。完全なる中立。
To be unsure of yourself is courage.
自分自身が不安なのは、勇気だ。
Courage is so many things.
勇気はたくさんのことだわ。
Courage is the courage of Aung San Suu Kyi,
勇気とは、アウンサンスーチーの勇気。
who is being kept
彼女はずっと、
incommunicado and under house arrest.
外部と連絡を絶たれ、 自宅に監禁されている。
Courage is the courage of
勇気とは、
the young students in Tiananmen Square.
天安門広場にいた学生の勇気。
We risk our lives in many different ways.
私たちは様々に命のリスクを冒します。
I've never really risked mine, so I can't say.
私はそんなリスクを 冒したことがありません。
I've never lived in truly dangerous situations.
私は真に危険な状況に さらされたことがありません。
The way so many people around this table have done.
このテーブルについている 多くの人とはちがって。
To put it simply, to be willing to die.
かんたんにいえば、 死を覚悟すること。
Yes, to be willing to die.
そう、死んでもいい、と思うこと。
To have the courage to take the risk to die,
自分であること、 自分のすることを守りぬくために
to defend who I am and what I'm doing.
死ぬリスクを冒す勇気。
Well, I mean, we're sitting in a square,
私たちが集まったこの広場で、
where the adventure of Nazism
かつてナチスの冒険が
took over this beautiful country of Germany,
美しい国ドイツの主導権を握り、
and distorted the laws of justice
正義の法を歪めた。
in a most gross and horrific fashion.
最も忌まわしく、おぞましいやり方で。
Imagine the courage of people that broke the laws of the state
想像してみてください、 あえて国の法に背いた勇気ある人々を。
to honour the higher law
より崇高な掟である、
of caring for human life.
人間らしさの名誉を守るために。
You don't know that Chinese prison labour camps
ご存じないでしょうが、 中国の刑務所の労働収容所は
are similar to Soviet gulags,
かつてのソ連の強制労働収容所や
or German concentration camps.
ドイツの強制収容所にそっくりです。
About 40 or 50 million people lost their lives there.
四千万、あるいは五千万人が そこで命を落としました。
I was there for 19 years,
私は、アメリカへ渡る前に
before I made it to America.
19年間、そこにいました。
I didn't want to talk about this,
この話はしたくなかったのですが、
but finally I have,
今ようやく話したのは、
because we have only one lifetime.
人生、一度きりだからです。
What would Argentina have been without the courage
アルゼンチンは、五月広場の 母親たちの勇気がなかったら、
of the Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo,
どうなっていただろうか。
who stood up to the dictatorships and terrorism
彼女たちは、独裁とテロに立ち向かった。
of the Generals Videla, Massera and Agosti,
ビデラ、マッセラ、 アゴスティという軍人らは
who "disappeared" thousands of people by throwing them into the sea.
何千人も海に投げ込み、 「行方不明者」を出した張本人たち。
What would have become of us
この不明者らの母親たちから
without the lesson in courage taught by these mothers,
勇気を学んでいなかったら、 どうなっていただろう？
who stood before the Casa de Gobierno every Thursday
彼女たちは毎週木曜日、 いなくなった息子たちの写真を抱えて
with the portraits of their disappeared sons?
大統領府の前に立ち続けた。
Courage means to understand
勇気とは、
that these powers are not invincible,
権力が絶対ではない、と確信すること。
as is being demonstrated by people in the world,
そのことを、世界中の人々が示したように。
who, with courage and indignation,
彼らは勇気と怒りをもって
have managed to expel transnationals from their countries,
他国の資本家を追い出し、
have managed to overthrow
政府を揺るがし、
and topple governments.
転覆させることに成功した。
Courage has everything to do with
勇気とは、正面きって
looking at the future in the face,
未来に目を向けること。
always acknowledging an element of the unknown,
未知なる部分があることを 知りつつも、信じるんだ。
but believing that if one sacrifices,
だれかが犠牲になり、
if one suffers,
だれかが苦しみ、
if one takes a risk and allows oneself to be vulnerable,
だれかが矢面に立って 危険を冒せば、
that one can still make a difference.
それだけで、なにかを変えられる、 ということを。
We should keep this in mind
念頭におくべきなのは、
and it should make us all the more radical and motivated,
私たちがもっと過激に、 もっと使命感をもつべきだということ。
as we don't risk our lives,
命がけでもなく、リスクといえば
just a little boredom,
せいぜい退屈を少々、
a little ostracism, a little of our well-being.
疎外を少々、豊かさを少々 危うくするだけなのだから。
Courage is also not just about changing this world.
勇気とは、 世界を変えることばかりじゃありません。
It is really also about ensuring
今の世の中が 私自身を変えはしない、と
that the present day world does not change me.
肝に銘じることでもあります。
Question 78.
問い78。
From Nancy Clemons, 57, Cameron, Missouri, USA...
ナンシー・クレモンスより、57歳、 キャメロン、ミズーリ州、米国...
"What can I do, and tell others to do, to stop global warming?"
「地球の温暖化防止に、 私は何ができ、人に何を促したらいいだろう？」
Please begin.
どうぞ、始めてください。
This is a big question.
これは壮大な問いね。
Quite simply, future generations will not be able to understand
未来の世代は、 理解できないことでしょう、
our delirium of destruction.
我々のやみくもな破壊ぶりを。
There's nothing we can do to stop global warming.
地球の温暖化に対し、 なす術はありません。
The ice is going to carry on melting away.
氷はどんどん溶け続けます。
And now the question is: Who will live?
そして問題は、だれが生きるか、です。
Who will live a life worth living?
だれが、生きる価値のある生活を 送れるでしょうか？
We know that many will perish.
おそらく、 大勢が命を失うでしょう。
We know that many more will barely survive with no life.
多くが命だけしか助からないでしょう。
Few will have a life worthy of living.
生きるに値する生活ができるのは ほんのわずかでしょう。
I pray to the Great One and ask him again and pray again
全能なる相手に向かい、 私は何度も願い、祈ります。
that you and me will be able to have a life worthy of living.
あなたや私が、 ありがたいと思える暮らしができるように。
Because no matter what you and I do today
なぜなら、私たちがどんなにあがいても
there's no way of returning.
もう引き返せないから。
The ice will carry on melting until it has ceased to exist.
氷は溶け続け、しまいにはなくなります。
Actually, we can't stop global warming any more.
地球の温暖化を阻止することは、 もう無理です。
As an evolution biologist, I firmly believe
進化生物学者として 私が確信しているのは、
that we cannot stop it any more.
もう、止められないということです。
However, we can slow it down.
ただし、遅らせることはできます。
Global warming is not about science. It's about experience.
地球温暖化は科学の問題ではなく、 経験の問題です。
Science will give us the facts, the data and it may move us to act.
科学は事実としてデータを提供し、 それを基に人は対処します。
But how we move each other to act is a question
しかし、 どうやって互いに行動を起こすかは、
more of the heart than of the head.
頭より、気持ちの問題なのです。
We are all part of the problem,
私たち自身が問題の一部であるように
but we can also be part of the solution.
解決法の一部にもなれるはずです。
I could make a contribution if I stop driving my car.
自動車に乗るのをやめることで 多少貢献できます。
Transitions to bio fuels and even large-scale wind and solar
バイオ燃料へ切り替えたり 大規模な風力、太陽発電設備を導入しても
would probably not be sufficient to sustain
おそらく、 現在の産業の力を持続させるには
an industrial system at the present scale.
不十分でしょう。
So the answer is powering down.
ですから、答えは 「パワーダウン」しかありません。
Right now, hundreds of communities are starting to take these steps.
現在、何百という自治体が まさにこれをやり始めています。
They are engaged in what is called "power down".
いわゆる「パワーダウン」と 取り組んでいるのです。
They are looking at how they as communities
自治体が模索しているのは、
can take steps right now to localize their economies.
経済を地元で賄っていくための方法です。
They realize that if oil prices shoot up or if there's scarcity,
経験上、石油の価格が高騰したり、 不足したりすると、
they may find the supermarket shelves empty.
スーパーの棚がたちまち空になります。
That they won't be able to heat their homes,
住居を暖房で暖めることもできず、
that they won't be able to travel.
旅行することもできなくなります。
We must talk about how to control
話し合うべきですね、 いかにして過剰な欲を
our cheap desire.
抑制するか。
I think something we can all do worldwide
私たちがどこにいても できることは、
is to shame and ridicule the people who are polluting.
公害を引き起こしている人々を 辱め、嘲笑することです。
There won't be any state of emergency.
非常事態にはならない。
We have been for thousands of years
もう何千年も前から
in a state of emergency.
緊急事態なのだから。
We delude ourselves into thinking
私たちは錯覚を起こす。それは
that these problems are the creation
国が、政治が、宗教を
of our nation, government, religion or race,
人種が、民族が 作り上げられていると思うけど、
but this is not so.
本来はそうではないのです。
The problem lies within
人類、ひとりひとりの
each individual's consciousness.
意識の問題であるのです。
I don't believe in humankind. No, I don't.
ぼくは人類を信じない。信じないよ。
I tell you, I'm embarrassed to belong to that race.
正直いって、 この品種に属していることが恥ずかしい。
And at the same time, I'm fascinated by it.
と同時に、 惹きつけられもするわけだけど。
La belle et la bestia.
美女と野獣だね。
Question 83
問い83は
is from the photographer Sebastião Salgado
写真家のセバスチャン・サルガドから。
of Aimorés, Minas Gerais, Brazil...
アイモレ、ミナスジェライス州、ブラジル。
"Can a person be perceptive enough to see our planet"
「人は、自分も自然の一部だ ということを悟るべく
"in a way that tells them that they too are part of nature?"
地球を見る目を備えているでしょうか？」
We all start seeing clearer and clearer the damage that's done.
我々は、ますますはっきりと 損害に気づき始めている。
We see it at our doorsteps.
それはもう、家の前まで来ている。
We see and feel the climate changes, the droughts and the flooding,
干ばつや洪水、嵐や猛暑で
the storms and the heat.
気候変動を見たり、感じたりする。
We breathe the bad air.
悪い空気を吸い、
We suffer from allergies.
アレルギーに悩まされる。
We miss the taste in food.
食べ物に味を感じない。
We watch the forest die,
森が死に、
the animals and plants endangered and disappearing.
動物や植物が絶滅するのを 目の当たりにする。
And more and more of us understand
そして、ますます多くの人が悟るのは、
that the planet does not belong to us,
地球が自分たちの物ではないということ。
but that we belong to the Earth.
むしろ、 自分たちが地球の一部だということ。
Since the 20th Century,
20世紀に
when man was able to escape gravity and move into space,
人間が地球の重力から解かれて 宇宙へいって以来、
we had pictures, beautiful pictures of our planet,
地球の美しい写真を 見ることができた。
that little bluish globe floating through the universe.
宇宙に浮かぶ、 少し青っぽい地球という星。
As you look at those pictures, you become almost sentimental and think:
これを見ただけで感傷的にさえなり、
I live on this planet, I am part of this planet.
自分はこの惑星に住み、 この惑星の一部なのだ、と実感する。
Go out into a field and lie down at night
夜、野原に出て寝転がり、
and look down into the stars.
星を見下ろしてごらんなさい。
Pretend gravity has you glued to the bottom of the planet,
重力があなたを惑星の下側に つけていると想像して。
because how do you know which way is up?
どっちが上かなんて、 わからないでしょう？
The reason why little children love animals is because
子供が動物を好きなのは、
we have co-evolved with the rest of creation.
私たち人間が他の創造物と共に 進化してきたからなの。
We have lived close to nature for almost all our evolution.
進化する間、いつもずっと 自然とつながっていた。
This little blip of modern life cut off from the Earth,
ただ、ここへきてほんのわずかな間に、 それを切り離してしまった。
cut off from other animals and cut off from one another
地球から、 ほかの動物から、ほかの人間から。
has only happened,
そうなってしまったのは、
because we've also become cut off from ourselves,
私たちが自分自身から、
from our own hearts, from our own bodies.
自らの心、自らの体から 切り離してしまったからなのよ。
Nature makes the most sophisticated materials on the planet
自然は、この地球において、 最も洗練された物質を
out of carbohydrates.
炭水化物からつくりだします。
We too can learn how to do that.
私たちは、それを学べます。
But we have thought ourselves to be superior to nature.
なのに、私たちは自然よりも 優れていると思い込んでいます。
We haven't looked at her four and a half billion years of experience
私たちは、自然が45億年の営みのなかで
in incredible technologies.
成し遂げてきた離れ業を顧みません。
Take a wasps' nest.
例えば、蜂の巣。
It's a building that hangs from a single thread
たった一本の糸にぶら下がる造りで、
made of material so light that it can hold
極めて軽い材料でできていますが、
three hundred times its own weight in inhabitants.
その三百倍もの住人の重量を 支えることができます。
Can we learn to make buildings like that?
そんな建設物を、 私たちは真似できますか？
Can we grow skyscrapers from the bottom up the way a reed grows,
葦が下から育つように 高層ビルを建てられますか？
by building new cells at the bottom of it and pushing itself upward?
新しい細胞を下で作り、 それを上に押し上げていくように？
We have so much to learn from nature.
私たちは、どれほど 自然から学べることでしょう。
It is by our own free choice,
結局のところ我々次第なのです、
by our personal efforts,
どれだけ努力して
that we will achieve balance with nature
自然とのバランスをつくりあげ、
and so become like all of nature.
自然の一部となり得るか。
Then we will feel
そうすれば
the eternity, perfection and harmony
自然の万物に宿る
that is everywhere in nature
永遠性、完璧性と調和を 実感することだろう。
except within our ourselves.
それは、我々自身には 宿っていない。
Everything we eat, everything we wear,
私たちが食するすべて、着るすべて、
all our houses, all our objects come from the living Earth.
住まい、もののすべてが 生きた地球からのもの。
Learning how to live from that Earth in a way that is sustainable
その地球から、 持続可能な生き方を学ぶのは、
is not utopian, is not a dream.
ユートピア的でも、夢でもない。
What stands between us and that possibility
私たちとその可能性の間に 立ちはだかるのは
is the idea that it can't be done,
それができないという思い込み。
the idea that they are too powerful,
相手が大きすぎるという思い込み。
that corporations can't change,
企業は変わらない、
the idea that people don't want change,
人は変わらない、という思い込み。
the idea that all of this comes from innate human greed,
すべては、 人の生来の欲が引き起こした結果だ、
that it comes from overpopulation.
人口過剰のせいだ、という思い込み。
The planet is too crowded,
地球は人口過剰、
therefore it's not possible to provide for people.
だから、全員を満たすことは不可能、 という思い込み。
All of these are myths that need to be reassessed,
これらすべては見直すべきことであり、
assumptions that need to be rethought.
考え直すべき億説でしかないの。
Question 96 comes from Miraj Khaled,
問い96はミライジ・カレッドからです、
30, from Dhaka, Bangladesh.
30歳、ダッカ、バングラデシュ。
"What is God's religion?", she asks.
「神の宗教は何？」という質問。
"What is God's religion?" Please begin.
「神の宗教は何？」 どうぞ、始めてください。
I loved that question when I saw it,
この問い、すごく気に入っているの。
because I think it's very perceptive.
だって、とても奥深いじゃありませんか。
Which God?
どの神だろう？
Which Religion?
どの宗教？
What God? Whose God?
なんの神様？だれの神様？
Whichever way we want to take it,
この問いをどう捉えようと、
we must respect how others
他者がこの「神」という言葉を どう捉えるか、
see this word "God".
尊重すべきですね。
God is a way of defining
神は、ある種 定義の表れだと思う。
certain archetypes,
特定の原型の定義、
certain expectations
特定の期待の定義、
and objectives.
特定の目的の定義。
God is "is-ness".
神とは、「存在すること」。
God is spirit. God is not religion. God doesn't have a religion.
神は霊。宗教じゃないわ。 神は宗教を持たないでしょ。
God doesn't exist.
神は存在しません。
The religion of my Goddess
私の神の信仰は、
is reflected in every corner of the world,
世のあるゆる所に反映されています。
in every... leaf,
どの葉っぱにも、
in every speck of dirt,
埃の塵にも、
in every... flower.
どの花にも。
No, I don't believe that God has a religion.
ぼくは、 神に宗教があるなんて思わない。
I think that religion is a profoundly human phenomenon.
宗教そのものが 限りなく人間臭いものだから。
When we talk about God having a religion,
神の宗教について語るとき、
you can rest assured
確実にいえることは、
that we're talking about some human construction,
それがあくまでも人間があつらえた、
some human creation.
人間の産物でしかないってことだ。
What we project onto Him.
我々が神に投影するのは、
I am of Love.
私は愛。
I am of the Universe.
私は宇宙。
I am God in Action.
私は活動する神。
There is no God.
神はいない。
God is a symbol for something
神は、言葉では表せない何かの
that we can't express in words.
象徴です。
And that's also why there's no God's religion.
ですから、神の宗教は存在しません。
God, we have to imagine, is something
神が何かというと、 こう考えればよろしいんじゃないでしょうか。
that is not only unknown to us,
未知というものではなく、
but is also beyond our knowledge,
知の範疇に当てはまらない、
that has no quality of being known.
知るという質のものではない、ということ。
It's as if we were to ask the question,
例えば、 こんな質問をするようなものです。
what is the colour of a circle?
「輪は何色？」と。
Is it red, green or blue?
赤、緑、それとも青？
It's neither blue nor red nor green.
いや、青でも赤でも緑でもない。
It's also not colourless.
でも、色がないわけではない。
The question about the colour of the circle is absurd,
色を尋ねることは無意味です、
because a circle knows no colour.
輪は色を知らないから。
Many people are unwilling to see this.
多くの人はこれを認めたがりません。
They take a pen out of their pocket,
ポケットからペンを取り出し、
draw a circle on a piece of paper
紙切れに輪を描いて
and say, "Look, this circle is blue."
「ほら、輪は青だよ」という。
Yes, the circle drawn by them is blue,
そう、そこに描かれた輪は たしかに青いけど、
but the colour comes from my pen,
その色はペンから出た色であって、
and not from the circle.
輪の色じゃありません。
The colour of the pen is the religion
ペンの色こそ宗教であり、
with which we express the divinity,
それで私たちは 神性を表そうとしますが、
but we cannot draw the circle ourselves.
輪そのものを描くことはできません。
It is something that has nothing to do with colours.
それは、色とは関係ないものなのです。
There are as many religions
色の数がたくさんあるように
as there are colours with which I can draw a circle.
宗教もたくさんあり、 それで輪を描けるのです。
I really like that one.
この問い、大好き。
I believe in God, but all I know about God is,
僕は神を信じる。 でも神について知っていることは
there is a God and it isn't me.
いる、というだけで それが私ではない、ということ。
That's all I know so far.
それだけしか知らない。
Don't you think God is in you as well?
でも、あなたの中にも 神はいるんじゃない？
Oh absolutely. Absolutely.
ああ、そうだね、もちろん。
Most of my whole thing with spirituality is...
僕の精神性の大部分は...
I'm a recovering heroin addict.
自分が麻薬中毒者だったことと 関係している。
I haven't met God yet.
私はまだ神に出会っていません。
If I meet Him one day,
でも、いつか会えたら、
then I will ask Him the questions.
そのことを尋ねます。
-Thank you. -Thank you, too.
-ありがとう。 -こちらこそ。
-Last one. -Question...
-最後よ。 -問い...
-100! -100.
-100！ -100。
-Last one. -I didn't think we'd make it!
-最後。 -いけるとは思わなかったな！
Okay, last question. Let's do it.
さあ、最後の問い、いきましょう。
From Keith Dierkx, 48, Piedmont, California, USA.
キース・ディルクス、48歳、 ピードモント、カルフォルニア州、米国。
"What are the myths that we need to create"
「よりよい世界にするために、
"to change the world for the better?"
私たちはどんな神話をつくるべきか？」
Creation stories are part of every culture in human history,
創造神話は、 あらゆる文化の人類史として登場します。
and they were usually told by some kind of a priesthood.
たいてい、 司祭のような立場の人が語りました。
But now science tells the creation story.
でも、今では科学が神話を語ります。
It has been elevated to that status of priesthood
科学が司祭の立場をとって代わり、
that gets to tell the big story to the culture.
各文化にその壮大な物語をきかせます。
What story is it telling us?
どんな物語でしょう？
That we live in a non-living, purposeless universe
私たちは、エントロピーで動く、
running down by entropy.
無生命であてもない世界に住んでいる、と。
Oh! How cheery is that for a creation story?
まあ、なんて楽しい創造神話かしら？
And then we add in that evolution on this planet
それから、こうつけ加えるんです。 地球上の進化は、
is about the survival of the fittest,
強者が生き残ること、
about an endless competition in scarcity,
欠乏による果てしない争奪戦、
and that you have to get what you can while you can
だれもがありったけ奪えるものを奪い、
and beat the other guy to it.
相手を打ち負かすことでした、と。
This is a totally depressing creation story,
まったく、 暗澹とした気持ちになる創造神話です。
a universe running down meaninglessly,
無意味に損なわれていく世界、
you're stuck in an endless struggle in scarcity.
欠乏による、 果てしない葛藤から逃れられません。
This is a terrible story to tell. It doesn't fit the scientific facts.
語るには、あまりにひどい話ですし、 科学的事実と一致していません。
Every force in nature has an opposite.
自然界では、作用があれば、 必ず反作用があります。
If there's entropy, there has to be syntropy.
エントロピーがあれば、 シントロピーがあります。
In evolution there's a tremendous amount of cooperation.
進化は、膨大な数の協力体制を 生み出してきました。
In fact, I'd say there's a great story
進化を遂げる品種の成熟過程は
in the maturation cycle of evolving species,
壮大な物語が実際にはあるのです。
where they first are young and grabby
最初は若くて貪欲で、
they multiply and take all the territory they can,
増殖してはどんどん縄張りを広げ、
bump off their competitors, act like capitalists.
競争相手を排除して まるで資本主義者のようにふるまいます。
And then they discover, bit by bit, the advantages of cooperation.
ですが、だんだんと 協力するメリットを見出すのです。
And, as they do so, they build bigger and bigger cooperative enterprises
そうするうちに、協力する体制の規模を どんどん拡張していき、
and find out that their economies are cheaper,
その方がもっと安上がりに、
more effective, more efficient, work for everybody,
もっと効果的、かつ効率的に みんなのためになることに気づくのです。
and you get the evolution of rainforests,
こうして熱帯雨林が進化を遂げ、
and human bodies made of a hundred trillion cells,
百兆もの細胞から成るヒトの体は
working in complete cooperation even though they're so diverse.
個々が異なる性質にも関わらず 完全な協力体制で機能しています。
This is a story we need to tell in the world, a great new story
これこそ、世界中に広めるべき 壮大な新しい物語であり、
of the human species growing up into global family,
人類が徐々に グローバルな家族へと成長し、
doing win-win economics and making a better world for all.
互いが得する経済をまわしつつ、 世の中を良くしていくのです。
Human beings are appreciators,
人間は、感謝する存在で、
not just observers but appreciators, participants,
単なる傍観者ではありません。 宇宙のプロセスを尊び、それに加わり、
even co-creators of the cosmic process.
創造を共に担う協力者でもあります。
The whole world is deeply entangled.
世界全体は、深く絡み合っています。
All the living organisms, all the parts of the universe.
生けるものすべて、宇宙のあらゆる部分。
The whole universe is living,
宇宙全体が生きているのです。
the electrons and the protons and everything.
電子も、陽子もなにからなにまで。
They are all organisms.
すべては有機体です。
They all have a history and they are all entangled so deeply,
それぞれの歴史があり、 互いに深いところで絡み合い、
intimately interconnected, that you cannot separate them.
緊密なつながりがあるので、 それらを切り離すことはできません。
And, at any moment, this entangled universe
そして、この絡み合った世界は絶え間なく
is creating and recreating itself anew.
自らを創り、 新たに創りなおしていくのです。
That, I think, is the evolution of the cosmos,
それが、 コスモスの進化だと思うのです。
the evolution of all things in it from atoms, to humans, to galaxies.
原子を始め、 人間から銀河に至るすべての進化です。
That is the objective. That is the ambition.
それが目指すものであり、 それが志すものです。
That is the ultimate aim of divine creativity.
それが、神的な創造性の最終目的です。
That's as far as we can come as human beings to understand it.
人間の理解は この点までならついていけます。
I believe
思うに…
in a measure of humility,
謙虚さの尺度と
and in a measure of humanity,
人間性の尺度、
and in an avowal of beauty
美の肯定が、
as an antidote to all the brutality,
世界におけるすべての残忍性、
and cruelty of the world.
冷酷さに抗う効力を 発揮するでしょう。
I believe
思うに、
that the sacred lives in nature,
神聖なるものは、 超自然の内のみならず、
not only in the supernatural,
自然の内に、
but also in the beauty of nature.
自然の美の内に 宿っているんじゃないでしょうか。
I believe
おそらく、
human beings are metaphysical animals,
人間は形而上学的な動物であり、
and always will be because of their mortality.
その有限性ゆえにそうあり続けるだろう。
The human is the only animal that knows it must die.
動物のなかで人間のみが、 死ぬことを自覚している。
This is the source of the mystery,
そこに謎が秘められ、
of the unending mystery of human existence.
人間の存在について 延々に続く謎がある。
It would have to do with the marrying of the mind,
重要なのは、心を融合させること、
the soul, and this corporeal little covering
魂の融合、そして、肉体と呼ばれている
that is supposed to be the body.
肉でできたちっぽけな容器の融合。
The marriage of all those,
こうした事柄の融合が、
if it indeed be that,
実際に起こるとしたら、
can only be powered by positivity.
それはポジティブさが原動力となる。
And if the positivity
そして、ポジティブさが
then manages to give birth to that marriage...
こうした融合を成し遂げられたら...
then all the troubles of the Earth will be gone.
地球上のあらゆる問題が なくなるだろう。
If the human mind has got the space
もしも、人の精神が空間を得て、
in which to breathe, to live, to pulse, to flow...
呼吸したり、生きたり、 脈を打ったり、流れたりできたら...
Who is ever going to listen to all of this?
果たしていったい、 だれがこれを全部きくんだ？
Because we're one hundred and twelve, there are a hundred questions.
というのは、我々は112人いて、 100の質問があるんだから。
That's 11,200. Let's say...
合わせると、11 200の答えだ。それを...
Only two minutes each time. That's 22,000 minutes.
各答えにつき、2分とすると 全部で22 000分。
You know what that is?
それって、どれくらいだと思う？
That's three hundred days.
500…いや、300日だよ。
Okay, we're finished.
よし、終わった。
It's over.
終わったよ。
Copyright © 2011 TITELBILD, Berlin Subtitle: S. Kirchner, V. Trespalacios
Copyright © 2011 TITELBILD, Berlin Subtitles: Sakae Nasuda